Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - Calabresi, Guido, 2006 March 30; computer file (WAV)
    Guido Calabresi was raised in New Haven, and received his BA from Yale College and his JD from Yale Law School. Calabresi discusses his connections to the Tyler Cooper law firm, a "progressive" firm, according to Calabresi, with deep roots in the New Haven community. Morris Tyler (Calabresi's father-in-law) was involved with the Dixwell Community House, while his partner Jim Cooper started the New Haven Foundation and Legal Aid in New Haven. Calabresi discusses the way in which lawyers can act a "force of good" in their communities, suggesting that this is the largest significance of jurists such as Cooper and Tyler. The Tyler Cooper firm would represent the city of New Haven in their "redevelopment" (i.e. Urban Renewal) plans in the 1960s and 1970s. Calabresi also discusses changes in the orientation of Yale Law School, suggesting that a localism and connection to New Haven that characterized an earlier generation of Law students has given way to a more national focus.
    Interviewer: Ruben, Gregory
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Carnegie, Edna, 2005 April 27; computer file (WAV)
    Edna Carnegie, the daughter of immigrants from Nevis (in the Caribbean), taught English in New Haven public schools for 25 years. She was among the first African Americans to teach in the New Haven public school system. Carnegie attended college at St. Augustine's Episcopal College in Raleigh, NC. She talks about going to college during the Great Depression, a luxury that was only made possible by the generosity of Carnegie's church in New Haven. She also talks about her experiences on segregated public transportation in the Jim Crow South. Along with her teaching, Carnegie was active in church and community organizations. She taught Sunday School for 40 years at St. Luke's Episcopal Church in New Haven, where she was also involved in the Girls Friendly Society. The Friendly Society allowed Carnegie to travel abroad on a number of occassions, including trips to Europe, Australia, and Israel. Carnegie was a founding member of Dwight Development Corporation, which was involved in community activism and organizing in the Dwight Street area, and was an active participant in the New Haven NAACP and the Civil Rights struggle.
    Interviewer: Okechukwu, Cynthia and Soltman, Daniel
    Length (min): 68
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Caron, Erna, 2007 March 1; computer file (WAV)
    Erna Carron has spent the better part of her life on Chatham Street, in Fair Haven. She was born and raised there, and, for the past 55 years, has lived one house down from the one in which she grew up. She discusses the "mom and pop" stores in the Chatham Street area, and the make-up of the community when she was young. She talks about her childhood friends and activities, and discusses the differences and similarities between her upbringing on Chatham Street and her children's'. Carron grew up in a German-speaking household, and compares this to the growing Spanish-speaking presence in Fairhaven today. Half-way through the interview, David Carron (Erna's son) joins in. He continues the conversation, talking about his childhood on Chatham Street, and the linguistic and cultural lines that divide Fair Haven.
    Interviewer: Ma, Ying-Ying
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Casey, John, 2005 February 28; 2 computer files (WAV). Originally recorded as two separate recording tracks with different audio channel configurations (Track 1 recorded in stereo, Track 2 recorded as mono). The processed master recording was converted entirely to stereo.
    Father John Casey grew up in the East Rock neighborhood of New Haven, attending St. Joseph's Parish on Edwards Street. After attending public schools in New Haven, Father Casey enrolled in Seminary and was sent to a number of parishes in the Hartford Diocese before his assignment to St. Boniface's in New Haven. Casey talks about history of Catholicism in New Haven, focusing in particular on the ethnic and national divisions within the city's Catholic population. At one time, Casey recalls, there were six Catholic parishes within two blocks of each other, each catering to a different national group -- Irish, Italian, French, German, Polish, and Lithuanian. The shifting demographics of New Haven, however, have forced the closure of a number of churches and have dulled the ethnic identities of those that have remained. Although St. Boniface had once been the "German church," Casey recalls, its parishioners were now mostly ethnic Italians. These changes, Casey says, are not necessarily for the worse, but mark an important change from an era in which Catholicism and ethnicity were central features of daily life for many New Haven residents.
    Interviewer: Mimnaugh, Emily
    Length (min): 47, 40
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Cavanagh, Robert, 2006 February 27; computer file (WAV)
    Robert Cavanagh was born and raised in Framingham, Massachusetts. He attended Yale College, then Yale Law School, graduating in 1959. Although he considered work in New York, Cavanagh accepted a job at Wiggin and Dana, a New Haven firm, after receiving his degree. Cavanagh's arrival coincided with the era of redevelopment in New Haven, spear-headed by Mayor Richard Lee and administrator Edward Logue. Cavanagh denies that redevelopment played much of a role in his decision to practice in New Haven, but brokering deals between the city and landowners formed much of his work. Cavanagh recognizes that the redevelopment effort failed in a number of important ways, but refuses to condemn Lee and Logue for their efforts. They were, he says, trying to do a good thing for the city of New Haven. Cavanagh also talks about his years practicing law, some of his favoite cases, and the relative advantages and disadvantages of a law career in a smaller city such as New Haven.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Chauncey, Henry "Sam", 2005 November 4; computer file (WAV)
    Henry "Sam" Chauncey Jr. was Special Assistant to Yale President Kingman Brewster during the 1970 Black Panther trials and May Day demonstrations and later became Secretary of the University. He recalls the University's strategies and decisions in regard to the demonstrations. Brewster and many faculty members, Chauncey explains, believed that the May Day demonstrators should be protected but that violence and riots should be averted at all cost. He discusses his collaboration with New Haven Chief of Police Jim Ahearn and their joint attempts to maintain order. He tells a story of preventing the Weathermen from coming for the demonstrations by arranging for their buses to be sabotaged and explains that this was done to avert a riot. Chauncey discusses the Black Panthers, who he believes were fundamentally good and not prone to violence. Rather, he explains, they represented just one part of the revolutionary climate of the day. Chauncey also describes his suspicion that President Richard Nixon and Attorney General John Mitchell conspired to blow up Yale's ice rink and Peace Building as part of their assault on liberal universities and the Eastern Establishment. He assesses Yale's changing relationship with the community in the early 1970s, its attempts to foster better community relations, and the internal reforms to admissions and curriculum that took place under Brewster.
    Interviewer: Clemente, Jean
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Childers, Sherman, 2005 April 25; computer file (WAV)
    Sherman Childers, born in North Carolina, recalls his experiences in the Civil Rights sit-ins while a college student at Johnson C. Smith University. He describes his adolescent passion for languages and talks about his later experiences teaching English and French in North Carolina and France. As a student and teacher, he discusses the racial atmosphere among black and white students, parents, teachers, and administrators and his experiences with racism during segregation and integration. He shares anecdotes showing how, as a child, adolescent, and adult, he encountered and confronted racism in the words, actions, and underlying thoughts of people whose behavior had never been challenged. He describes the U.S. Black Power movement, mentioning groups such as SNCC and the Black Panthers and leaders such as Martin Luther, King and Bobby Seale. He also discusses his perception of race relations in France and shares his perspective of the popular culture of black youth then and today in music, dress, and recreation.
    Interviewer: Lechner, Emily and Dowe, Andrew
    Length (min): 75
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Cimino, Rose, 2004 December 6; computer file (WAV)
    Rose Cimino was born and raised in Fair Haven. She and her husband have run Apicella's Bakery on Grand Avenue in Fair Haven since the 1970s. She talks about many white New Havener's perceptions of Fair Haven as "dangerous," and talks about her experiences living and working in a racially and ethnically mixed community. Cimino is a leader of GABA -- the Grand Avenue Business Association -- which represents the diverse array of small businesses located on Grand Avenue. She discusses the challenges faced by small business owners in Fair Haven, which Cimino describes as New Haven's "step-sister," and GABA's attempts to get attention and assistance from the city of New Haven and its politicians.
    Interviewer: Sanchez, Christina
    Length (min): 41
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Clark, Francis, 2003 November 18; computer file (WAV)
    Francis Clark is an alderwoman in New Haven, the former Executive Director of the Arts Council and a Staff Member of the Connecticut Commission on the Arts. Clark was born and raised in New York City, and came to New Haven in 1956. She discusses Mayor Richard Lee's redevelopment programs in the 1960s, focusing specifically on the development of Audubon Street. As part of the city's efforts to revive its downtown, leading New Haven citizens fought for the construction of an arts center, to be located on Audubon Street. After a flurry of work in the 1960s, the Audubon program stalled for a decade. It was resumed in the 1980s, and now stands as a center of the arts in downtown New Haven, housing the Arts Council and the Neighborhood Music School. Clark recognizes that the redevelopment efforts failed in many important ways, including an insensitivity to pre-existing community structures, but she insists that the developers' intentions were noble. Clark mentions that she has lived through three periods in which a tangible excitement and a sense of possibility filled the city of New Haven: the redevelopment years of the 1960s; the early 1980s, when aspects of redevelopment left unfinished were picked up again; and recent years.
    Interviewer: Dolan, Thomas
    Length (min): 80, (6)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Cofield, Curtis, 2005 March 23; computer file (WAV)
    Curtis Cofield came to New Haven in 1965 to serve as Pastor for the Immanuel Baptist Church, on Chapel Street. Cofield describes the challenges of being a pastor of a predominantly middle-class, African-American congregation in the midst of the Civil Rights movement. His congregation, he explains, did not expect him to be radical and Cofield took a moderate liberal stance on many issues. He discusses the intimidation he experienced from the Black Panthers and other more radical groups. He opposed the violence and destruction that he believed characterized their message. Cofield labored to bridge gaps in the community through inter-congregational collaboration. He talks a bit about the May Day demonstrationsand the attempts to improve racial relations in their aftermath. He also talks about the economic aspects of the Civil Rights movement.
    Length (min): 31
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Cohen, Marvin, 2006 January 19; computer file (WAV)
    Marvin Cohen was born and raised in New Haven, and, after college, returned to the city to open a nursery. Asked by Art Spiegel (creator of the graphic novel Maus) to design a Holocaust memorial for New Haven. Cohen offered a simple design, featuring a Star of David and thirteen evergreen trees. His sketch was supplemented with work by architect Gus Franzoni, and the memorial placed on Whalley Avenue near Edgewood Park. Cohen describes the difficulties in finding an appropriate place for the memorial, and a number of challenges from within the Jewish community regarding the propriety and design of the monument. Cohen shares a number of his scrapbooks and his memorabilia with the interviewer.
    Interviewer: Brown, Michael
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Daniels, John, 2006 March 2; computer file (WAV)
    John Daniels was mayor of New Haven between 1990 and 1994. He was born and raised in the city, and attended Villanova University on a football scholarship. He credits his interest in politics to two distinct events: a meeting with New Haven Mayor Dick Lee when Daniels was a senior in High School, and Daniels' volunteer work on John F. Kennedy's presidential campaign in 1960. His political career began with a spot on the Board of Alderman, as a replacement Alderman for the 19th Ward. At that time, the 19th was the only ward represented by an African-American alderperson. Daniels served as an Alderman for 16 years, then served 10 years as State Senator, and finally 4 years as Mayor of New Haven. Daniels talks about the place of African Americans in the New Haven community, suggesting that many white people in the city are invested in keeping black people relegated to the bottom rungs of society. Even during his four years as Mayor, Daniels says, African Americans never really had control of the city. Daniels bemaons the current state of the city of New Haven, noting the lack of dissenting voices against the policies of Mayor John DeStefano, and describing what he sees as a concerted attempt to run poor Hispanics and African Americans out of the city in order to return New Haven to a white majority.
    Interviewer: Amos, Courtney
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 34U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Dawson, Che, 2007 May 4; computer file (WAV)
    Che Dawson was born and raised in Bridgeport, CT, but retained close ties to the New Haven community. In 1994, while in college, Dawson took a summer job as a counselor at LEAP (Leadership, Education, and Athletics in Parternship) in the Church Street South neighborhood of New Haven. LEAP was founded in 1992. The experience changed Dawson's life and career path, and after college, Dawson returned to New Haven to work full time with LEAP. Dawson describes the manner in which the LEAP program affects not only the students and communities it serves, but its counselors and employees as well. Dawson learned the importance of self-sacrifice and commitment through the program. The secret to LEAP's success, Dawson suggests, is its continuing commitment to, and connection with, familes and communities. LEAP proved itself to be trustworthy and effective, and, in so doing, was able to integrate itself more deeply into the fabric of the communities it served. At the time of the interview, Dawson had left LEAP.
    Interviewer: Howard, Meg
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Debenedet, Harry, 2003 November 20; computer file (WAV)
    Harry Debenedet, the son of Italian immigrants, grew up in the Hill Section of New Haven before moving to North Haven at age 12. As an adult he worked as a police officer in New Haven County. Debenedet discusses his participation in several Italian American societies in New Haven, including the Marchegiano Society, the Saint Andrew Society, the Santa Maria Maddalena Society. Debenedet was also a founding member of the Police Order of Centurions, an Italian American fraternal organization. He gives the history of these groups, recounting that most began as mutual aid societies organized around the Italian town from which its members emigrated. Today, Debenedet notes, the remaining societies focus on connecting Italian Americans and preserving their national cultural heritage. Debenedet also talks about the Italian neighborhoods of New Haven, explaining that northern Italians tended to live in the Hill section while southern Italians lived in the Wooster Street area. He then discusses the effects of urban renewal (refrred to as redevelopment) on the Italian neighborhoods and communities of New Haven and states that it "destroyed" the Hill Neighborhood. The various societies, he suggests, help maintain connections among second and third generation Italian Americans.
    Interviewer: Smith, Katherine
    Length (min): 38
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 36U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Devane, Milton, 2006 April 13; computer file (WAV)
    Milton Devane was born in New Haven in 1929, attended Yale College in the late 1940s, and graduated from Yale Law School in 1958 after serving in the Navy during the Korean War. Devane then went on to work for the Tyler Cooper law firm in New Haven, which represented the New Haven Redevelopment Agency in the 1960s. Devane discusses the culture of Yale Law school in the 1950s and admits that he chose Yale in part because it was a less cutthroat and less traditional school than Harvard. He then discusses working for Morris Tyler and James Cooper. He describes them as great mentors to young lawyers and committed to the New Haven community and to the law profession. Much of the interview focuses on the Redevelopment Agency's activities and the relationships between Development Administrator Edward "Ed" Logue, the Tyler Cooper firm, and the New Haven community. Devane admits that some mistakes were made in New Haven's urban renewal activities but criticizes the "revisionists" who only find fault in redevelopment.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - DiGioia, Pauline, 2007 February 17; computer file (WAV)
    Pauline DiGioia grew up in Hamden in a working-class, Italian-American family. In the early 1950s she worked at the A.C. Gilbert toy factory as a secretary but left after three and a half years to raise her children. Nevertheless, DiGioia developed lifelong relationships with her colleagues, who came to call themselves the "Gilbert Girls." She remembers her years at A.C. Gilbert as very happy times and remarks that Gilbert cared a lot about his employees. She describes the yearly summer picnics and Christmas dinners that he organized for his employees and their families. DiGioia also talks about growing up in Hamden and recounts stories of being a child, going to the beach, and her family life at home. She talks about her Italian grandparents and Italian American parents and their hard-working natures. After leaving the A.C. Gilbert company, she took college courses in physical education, raised her children, and participated in the Hamden Women's Club and in several golf clubs. She also encouraged her daughters to take up swimming. After her husband retired, DiGioia worked as an administrative assistant at several jobs at Yale University. At the time of the interview, she resides in Branford, where she swims, golfs, volunteers, and enjoys her grandchildren.
    Interviewer: Horowitz, Adam
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Dimow, Joe, 2004 November 15; computer file (WAV)
    Joe Dimow moved to New Haven in 1945 after being discharged from the army and became involved in political activism and community programs in the late 1950s and 1960s. Dimow and his wife first lived in the Hill section of New Haven and he worked in an automotive machine shop. Dimow had been the chair of the Communist Party in Hartford Connecticut and later became involved in the NAACP and the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE). He discusses how the McCarthy era and the subsequent rise of the New Left at the end of the 1950s changed the political climate in 1960s New Haven. The interview focuses on Dimow's experiences with African American politics and his community activities with the West Hills Neighborhood Corporation. He talks a great deal about the Black Panthers, whom he had mixed feelings about. While he admired their activities, he worried that they were too militant. Dimow also describes the relationship between the Black Panthers and the New Haven Jewish Community and discusses the issue of black anti-Semitism in the 1960s. He talks about the New Haven Black Panther trials, the administrations of Richard Lee and Edward Logue, and the liberal political activities of Rabbi Bob Goldburg and lawyer John Williams. He also discusses the ways that Yale University contributed to the "liberal stmosphere" of 1960s New Haven.
    Interviewer: Stubert, Lee
    Length (min): 63
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Dobihal, Rev. Ed, 2005 February 28; computer file (WAV)
    Edward Dobihal moved to Hamden in 1964 and spent his career in New Haven working at the Yale Divinity School and as Chaplain at Yale New Haven Hospital. He discusses the role of churches in the Civil Rights movement, in both New Haven and in the southern United States. He also talks about the changing relationship between New Haven's churches in the early 1970s. Dobihal came to Connecticut from Washington D.C., where he had participated in the 1963 March on Washington. A member of the First Methodist Church, Dobihal was part of a community of politically active church members in New Haven that included figures such as William Sloan Coffin. Dobihal talks about the climate Civil Rights movement and compares New Haven's political and racial climate to places he knew in the South, and also considers the different levels of church involvement in the movement in the North and the South. He touches on the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, integration, the role of interfaith, interracial churches in the civil rights struggle, and other related issues. Dobihal then discusses the early 1970s and the tensions that split the New Haven Council of Churches. He took part in forming Downtown Cooperative Ministries, which became Interfaith Cooperative Ministries, after the 1970 May Day demonstrations. He talks about trying to unite congregations for social change across racial and faith lines, including the growing Black Muslim populations. Dobihal mentions that he was one of several New Haven residents whose phones were illegally wiretapped by the government in this era.
    Length (min): 69
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Donohue, Bill, 2004 November 26; computer file (WAV)
    Length (min): 36
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 41U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Dynia, Henry, 2005 March 9; computer file (WAV)
    Henry Dynia worked for Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo Associates, the architectural frim that designed the New Haven Coliseum. Dynia discusses the design of the Coliseum, mentioning that it was designed to compliment the existing Knights of Columbus building. He says that Kevin Roche designed the building during a "Brutalist, minimalist period" in architecture. He states that the Coliseum was a bold design for its time, something he believes the public has largely misunderstood. Dynia then discusses the problems that plagued the Coliseum after it opened in 1972. He blames the largely vacant Ninth Square neighborhood, fears of crime in the area, a lack of long-term planning for upgrades and improvements, and ineffective advertising for the Coliseum's disappointing existence and ultimate structural decline. But he also believes that the Coliseum and its parking spaces are important for New Haven and was upset when the mayor decided to demolish it before asking for more community input.